<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
  <title>echevarria.io</title>
  <description>Ivan Echevarria's blog</description>
  <link>https://www.echevarria.io</link>
  <item>
    <title>March 2022 – June 2023</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="photograph of the shoes my wife and I wore when we married" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/march-2022-to-june-2023/marriage-shoes.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's been a &lt;em&gt;long&lt;/em&gt; time since I did one of these updates. The big changes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;got married&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;finished the &lt;a href="https://bradfieldcs.com/csi/"&gt;Bradfield CSI&lt;/a&gt; coursework&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;started riding bikes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;switched teams at work from product to infrastructure&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="march-2022"&gt;March 2022&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I start the Bradfield CSI Operating Systems module.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reach 6 months at my job. I remember one of my interviewers saying that the firm will take as much as you give, that exercising boundaries is important. I'm not exercising my boundaries well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I invite a friend to my house under false pretenses ("we're going to grill") and make him instead apply to several dozen jobs. He gets some offers and decides to work in a lab. Later in the year, the company promotes him to designing and setting up labs. They move him to Pittsburgh in early 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="april-2022"&gt;April 2022&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I visit a college friend in Austin and help him set up his garage for woodworking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I go to the Oakland Zoo. The gibbons (small apes, not monkeys) are my favorite. They're kept in pairs in enclosures with shallow moats and very low fences – they could easily leave. But they like their islands and their arranged marriages, so they choose to stick around. I wonder how many people would be happier like this: paired up, given an island, provided for by super-intelligent space aliens.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The chimps are in a giant cage. Can't trust them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finish the Bradfield CSI Operating Systems module. My biggest takeaway is how constructed, how arbitrary it all is, much more so than databases or networks. I think this is because there are more degrees of freedom and fewer objective measures of what an operating system is or should be. I start the Bradfield CSI Databases module.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At work, the firm lays off 9% of employees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="may-2022"&gt;May 2022&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I visit Yosemite with my fiancée and two of our friends. What a place! The depth of the valley never registered until I actually visited.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My fiancée and I stay in Portland, OR for 10 days for a friend's wedding. The wedding is lovely. I ride an electric &lt;a href="https://biketownpdx.com/"&gt;BIKETOWN&lt;/a&gt; bike and am blown away. I resolve to buy an ebike when I get home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finish the Bradfield CSI databases module.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Song of the month: "Blessing" by Alex G.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe class="bandcamp-player" style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/track=2712508306/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/transparent=true/" seamless&gt;&lt;a href="https://sandy.bandcamp.com/track/blessing"&gt;Blessing by Alex G&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id="june-2022"&gt;June 2022&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I visit Virginia for a wedding. Go up to NYC for one night. Meet a friend late at night in Koreatown, get a giant plate of dessert. Stay in a wretched little room in a hotel with tiny communal bathrooms. In the morning I don't have time to wait in line for the shower. Go to the Guggenheim and get some good pizza with coworkers. Catch my train back to Virginia.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I buy an ebike in California. I ride it a lot, farther than I ever have before on bicycle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I start the CSI Distributed Systems module.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Song of the month: "Back in our Town" by Ivy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe class="bandcamp-player" style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=272457084/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/track=1716312549/transparent=true/" seamless&gt;&lt;a href="https://ivy-band.bandcamp.com/album/apartment-life-25th-anniversary-edition"&gt;Apartment Life (25th Anniversary Edition) by Ivy&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id="july-2022"&gt;July 2022&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I help a friend move; I rent a U-Haul van and drive it. My fiancée and I hike up Montara mountain. No view at all because of the fog, but that was its own kind of fun. My mom visits. She likes the ebike a lot. My sister visits a little later. It's her first time in the Bay Area in five years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I start the Bradfield CSI System Design module.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At work, there are credible rumors of another, larger round of layoffs. I am deeply ambivalent at the prospect of being laid off. I oscillate from wanting it very badly to being afraid of what it will do to my ego. I am giddy at the prospect of severance, of being forced to go my own way. But I also know that my father worked in software and was never laid off, even when his employer shrank from hundreds to a few dozen. If I leave I want it to be on my own terms, but I also believe I won't leave soon without getting laid off. I want to get to at least a year at the firm. But then I think about all the free time I could have to ride bicycles, read books, and program...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I send a message to a colleague who I respect to share with the rest of my team if I'm laid off. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="august-2022"&gt;August 2022&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm at the office when the firm lays of 23% of employees. I'm sad for the many I know. I oscillate between relief and disappointment for myself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://robinhood.com/us/en/support/articles/partner-stock-program/"&gt;product I worked on for the last several months&lt;/a&gt; launches. I watch closely for the duration of the program. I care a lot about the customers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finish the Bradfield CSI System Design module. What an incredible experience. For each of the problems, I use everything I've learned in the last year of the Bradfield CSI to sketch my solutions. That's the end of Bradfield coursework. It was so worthwhile.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I buy an iPhone. It's a really good piece of hardware running quite good software. It's nice to use something that &lt;em&gt;just works&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I realize that I don't actually need the electric assist in the bicycle. I buy a bicycle from &lt;a href="https://www.boxdogbikes.com/"&gt;Box Dog Bikes&lt;/a&gt; and ride it a lot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="september-2022"&gt;September 2022&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I reach 1 year at my job. Have a reputation for reliability and rigor. I am competent and unhappy. In my notes I write this is not the work I aspire to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Songs of the month: "Collage of Dreams" by John Beltran and "Kaini Industries" by Bibio.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe class="bandcamp-player" style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=770281207/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/track=551258983/transparent=true/" seamless&gt;&lt;a href="https://peacefrog.bandcamp.com/album/ten-days-of-blue-album"&gt;Ten Days Of Blue (Album) by John Beltran&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;iframe class="bandcamp-player" style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=2893281365/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/track=1655022122/transparent=true/" seamless&gt;&lt;a href="https://warprecords.bandcamp.com/album/warp20-recreated"&gt;Warp20 (Recreated) by Bibio&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id="october-2022"&gt;October 2022&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align: center;"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-horiz" style="width: 45%;" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/march-2022-to-june-2023/marriage-fitzgerald.jpg" alt="photo of husband and wife in a grove of trees"/&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-horiz" style="width: 45%;" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/march-2022-to-june-2023/marriage-chapel.jpg" alt="photo of bride and groom in a municipal building"/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife and I marry. Her brother, my sister are our witnesses. We go to the courthouse in the morning, get lunch at &lt;a href="https://www.lafondasanmateo.com/menu"&gt;La Fonda&lt;/a&gt;, and visit &lt;a href="https://www.smcgov.org/parks/fitzgerald-marine-reserve"&gt;Fitzgerald Marine Reserve&lt;/a&gt; after.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My dad visits a bit later. We ride bikes along the San Francisco Bay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At work, I tell my manager I want to switch teams. He's immediately supportive and introduces me to other managers. I begin an exhaustive search for my next team within the firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="november-2022"&gt;November 2022&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My wife and I go to Scottsdale for Thanksgiving. Visit Tempe and like it &lt;em&gt;a lot&lt;/em&gt;. I see &lt;a href="https://culdesac.com/"&gt;Culdesac&lt;/a&gt; in person.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At work, the most senior engineers at the firm take time to speak with me. They think my interests line up best with the Service Discovery and Communication (SD&amp;amp;C) or Container Orchestration (CO). I start the process of joining SD&amp;amp;C.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="december-2022"&gt;December 2022&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="photograph of my wife and I before our luncheon to celebrate our marriage" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/march-2022-to-june-2023/family-dinner.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My wife and I spend our first Christmas together in Virginia. We put on a small luncheon to celebrate our marriage with some of my family.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We go to a wedding in Charlottesville with her parents. It's a nice town. I particularly like &lt;a href="https://www.bluewhalebooks.com/"&gt;Blue Whale Books&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At work, my team switch is officially ok'd. I am thrilled with the level of support I've gotten through the entire process. I am happy I decided to look inside the firm instead of leaving.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the company Christmas party, I oafishly tell a user researcher I've worked with before that I'm switching teams because I want to work with computers more and people less. In hindsight, this isn't even true.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Song of the month: "Headroom Piano" by Alex G.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe class="bandcamp-player" style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1701099020/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/track=2630722265/transparent=true/" seamless&gt;&lt;a href="https://sandy.bandcamp.com/album/god-save-the-animals"&gt;God Save The Animals by Alex G&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id="january-2023"&gt;January 2023&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My friend and I take Caltrain to South San Francisco and hike our bikes up to the top of San Bruno Mountain. Ride the trail at the top. It's terrible for bicycles. Eventually get to the parking lot where there's a sign forbidding bikes from going on the trail we were on. Makes sense!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm only riding my regular bike, so I sell the ebike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At work, I start on SD&amp;amp;C. My teammates are citing manpages at each other. I love it. My manager and I hit it off immediately. It turns out he read &lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/flowers-make-a-nice-gift/index.html"&gt;Flowers make a nice gift&lt;/a&gt; when I first wrote it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="february-2023"&gt;February 2023&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My college friend visits the SF Bay for &lt;a href="https://www.effectivealtruism.org/ea-global/events/ea-global-bay-area-2023"&gt;EA Global&lt;/a&gt;. I take a Bradfield friend to dinner with this college friend and go to an EA Global afterparty. We stay for a half hour. It reminds all three of us of undergrad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I &lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/file:///Users/ivan/Github/iechevarria.github.io/blog/caltrain-ridership/index.html"&gt;make&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://caltrainridership.com/"&gt;caltrainridership.com&lt;/a&gt; out of frustration at how hard it was to get simple ridership numbers from Caltrain itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Songs of the month: "Naqi" by Mansur Brown, "Angelo Azzuro" by SSIEGE.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe class="bandcamp-player" style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=3110060064/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/track=1214958008/transparent=true/" seamless&gt;&lt;a href="https://mansurbrown.bandcamp.com/album/naqi-vol-2"&gt;NAQI Vol.2 by Mansur Brown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;iframe class="bandcamp-player" style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=103704281/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/track=121340449/transparent=true/" seamless&gt;&lt;a href="https://theyouthlabel.bandcamp.com/album/ssiege-fading-summer-yocs2"&gt;SSIEGE - Fading Summer - YOCS2 by YOUTH&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id="march-2023"&gt;March 2023&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I go to an &lt;a href="https://oxide.computer/"&gt;Oxide&lt;/a&gt; event. It's just like an episode of &lt;a href="https://oxide.computer/podcasts/oxide-and-friends"&gt;Oxide and Friends&lt;/a&gt;, but with more profanity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="photograph of an oxide computer company sled" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/march-2022-to-june-2023/oxide-sled.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Oxide folks bring hardware for people to pass around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="photograph of an oxide computer company board" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/march-2022-to-june-2023/oxide-board.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Storms keep me inside for more of the month than I would like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Song of the month: "Forest on the Sun" by Thrupence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe class="bandcamp-player" style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=3956203677/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/track=3353617191/transparent=true/" seamless&gt;&lt;a href="https://thrupence.bandcamp.com/album/ideas-of-aesthetics-lp"&gt;Ideas of Aesthetics (LP) by Thrupence&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id="april-2023"&gt;April 2023&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align: center;"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-horiz" style="width: 45%;" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/march-2022-to-june-2023/scottsdale-cake.jpg" alt="husband and wife with cake"/&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-horiz" style="width: 45%;" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/march-2022-to-june-2023/scottsdale-tables.jpg" alt="tables set up for a marriage celebration"/&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My wife and I go to Scottsdale to celebrate our marriage with her family. Her parents put on a beautiful event in their home and backyard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We go to Tempe with my parents. I like it a &lt;em&gt;lot&lt;/em&gt; less than last time. It's noisy and full of people. I realize my I only liked it last November because it was empty, and I love empty cities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Songs of the month: "Sunrise" by Young American Primitive, "Digital Arpeggios" by Percussions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe class="bandcamp-player" style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1116396347/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/track=901399245/transparent=true/" seamless&gt;&lt;a href="https://youngamericanprimitive.bandcamp.com/album/young-american-primitive"&gt;Young American Primitive by Young American Primitive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;iframe class="bandcamp-player" style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/track=3520133569/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/transparent=true/" seamless&gt;&lt;a href="https://percussions.bandcamp.com/track/digital-arpeggios"&gt;Digital Arpeggios by Percussions&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h2 id="may-2023"&gt;May 2023&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="photograph of friends at dinner" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/march-2022-to-june-2023/friends-dinner.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My wife and I celebrate our marriage with some friends at a picnic, dinner, and lunch. The photo above captures the vibe of the dinner (rowdy) pretty well. Somebody takes a picture of their bare ass with an instant camera. I catch up with folks I haven't seen in several years. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I scan a lot of photos afterward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="photograph of my table as I scanned photos" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/march-2022-to-june-2023/scanning.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="june-2023"&gt;June 2023&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I visit Portland and do one last little marriage celebration, a backyard barbecue with my Mom's family. My wife and I go to &lt;a href="https://www.instagram.com/parallelworldsbookshop/"&gt;Parallel Worlds&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.instagram.com/melville_books"&gt;Melville Books&lt;/a&gt;. I pick up a copy of &lt;em&gt;A Canticle for Leibowitz&lt;/em&gt; and nearly finish it in a day. It's my favorite piece of fiction ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With my newfound interest in Catholic monastic life via &lt;em&gt;Canticle&lt;/em&gt;, I come home and play &lt;a href="https://pentiment.obsidian.net/"&gt;Pentiment&lt;/a&gt; straight through in a weekend. It's great, it takes real advantage of the medium. And it doesn't have the tinge of being made for adolescents that most other games have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At work, I am refining a single design doc. It's not fun for a while, but then it becomes really fun: the most senior engineer at the firm gives an exceptionally thorough and rigorous review. Being forced to answer these questions gives me more confidence in my proposal. He approves the design. This is a highlight in my time at the firm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I enjoy my commute. I walk through a nice neighborhood to a train station, work on the train, walk through a nice neighborhood, and get to the office. I call friends on my walk home. I like the train (when it's not extremely and unpredictably delayed), and I like all the walking.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jul 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/march-2022-to-june-2023/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/march-2022-to-june-2023/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Caltrain ridership</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Caltrain's ridership numbers are a pain to get a hold of, so I made &lt;a href="https://caltrainridership.com"&gt;caltrainridership.com&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you go to Caltrain's official &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20220629064038/https://www.caltrain.com/about-caltrain/statistics-reports/ridership"&gt;ridership page&lt;/a&gt;, you get links to three different sources, only one of which, the Caltrain Board of Directors monthly meeting agendas, is up-to-date. Each agenda PDF has at most a year of ridership numbers, but some only have the actual average weekday ridership number for that specific month. The format has changed several times, so it's not even doable to programmatically extract ridership numbers. It shouldn't be this hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I read through old meeting agendas and found individual months' average weekday ridership back to July 2017. I dropped these numbers in a CSV which you can go get for yourself in the &lt;a href="https://github.com/iechevarria/caltrain-ridership"&gt;project GitHub repo&lt;/a&gt;. And I picked up the &lt;a href="https://caltrainridership.com"&gt;caltrainridership.com&lt;/a&gt; domain and made a little site with graphs and a table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It took effort to collect these numbers in the real world – distributing them should be the easy part. If Caltrain won't, I will.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Mon, 20 Feb 2023 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/caltrain-ridership/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/caltrain-ridership/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Bill and Ted and what art is for</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bill and Ted's Excellent Adventure&lt;/em&gt; is funny, stylish, and imaginative. I think it's close to perfect. It's also, at least in part, an ironic reflection on how ineffective art is as a tool for social change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The film ends with a character explaining how Bill and Ted's band shapes the course of history:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="quote"&gt;
"Wyld Stallyns' music has become the foundation of our whole society... eventually your music will help put an end to war and poverty. It will align the planets and bring them into universal harmony, allowing meaningful contact with all forms of life, from extraterrestrial beings to common household pets. And... it's excellent for dancing."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's so overblown – aligning the planets? The hyperbole is funny on its face. But this absurd grandeur also invites us to consider the real ambitions of those who forgot that art &lt;a href="http://mason.gmu.edu/~rnanian/Auden-InMemoryofYeats.html"&gt;makes nothing happen&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent history is littered with such failure. Kurt Vonnegut said this about artists' efforts to stop the Vietnam War:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="quote"&gt;
"[E]very artist worth a damn in this country, every serious writer, painter, stand-up comedian, musician, actor and actress, you name it, came out against [our war in Vietnam]. We formed what might be described as a laser beam of protest, with everybody aimed in the same direction, focused and intense. This weapon proved to have the power of a banana-cream pie three feet in diameter when dropped from a stepladder five-feet high."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If your highest priority is solving a concrete problem like hunger or poverty, art is the wrong tool. "[P]oems and pictures cannot by themselves save anyone." &lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/bill-and-ted-on-art/index.html#note-1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; At some point, you need to actually move food or money or whatever else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this is to say that art is useless or not worthwhile &lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/bill-and-ted-on-art/index.html#note-2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. Others have written better than I can about art's value &lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/bill-and-ted-on-art/index.html#note-3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;, but put simply, art reveals beauty that clarifies life, and it helps us endure. The best art is made with knowledge of its power – and its limits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1]&lt;i id="note-1"&gt; Robert Adams in his essay Photographing Evil&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2]&lt;i id="note-2"&gt; I'm writing this because of how seriously I take art, not because I want to diminish it.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3]&lt;i id="note-3"&gt; Robert Adams's book &lt;a href="https://aperture.org/books/beauty-in-photography/"&gt;Beauty in Photography&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://github.com/iechevarria/reading-notes/blob/master/2021/beauty-in-photography-adams-1981.md"&gt;(my notes)&lt;/a&gt; contains my favorite writing about art's purpose and limits.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/bill-and-ted-on-art/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/bill-and-ted-on-art/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>February 2022</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;I spent many of my weekends and evenings working on the Data Structures for Storage and Retrieval module of the &lt;a href="https://bradfieldcs.com/csi/"&gt;Bradfield CSI&lt;/a&gt;. I think this may have been my favorite yet. Unlike your typical data structures class, the Bradfield one focused on practical applications of data structures and is centered around implementing a key-value database from scratch. In the process, I learned about skip lists, SSTables, and Bloom filters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="vacuuming"&gt;Vacuuming&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't like sweeping, so looked for and bought a vacuum that does a good job with hard floor pickup. In the process of searching, I fell deep into the rabbit hole of vacuum YouTube. Some videos have vacuum reviewers running vacuums through precise and reproducible vacuum tests. Others have vacuum enthusiasts demonstrating old vacuums and lecturing about vacuum history.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It's all amazing. The enthusiasm is contagious. I had tickets for a concert on one Friday night, but I stayed home and skipped it because I wanted to read about vacuums instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I ended up with a Dyson V7 with a fluffy cleaner head, and I've been really enjoying it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="watching"&gt;Watching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bill and Ted's Excellent Adventure&lt;/em&gt; was excellent, and it was a more cutting satire I was expecting. I think it's extremely pessimistic about art's ability to change the world, a perspective I'm sympathetic to. I intend to write more about this.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also saw &lt;em&gt;La La Land&lt;/em&gt; for the first time this month. I initially thought it was a story about weak-willed people and that if the two leads were so in love, they should have made more of an effort to be together. But my girlfriend changed my mind a bit by pointing out how short-lived the central relationship is and that the movie sort of subverts the typical Hollywood romance.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/february-2022/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/february-2022/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Bradfield School of Computer Science is phenomenal</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nobody asked me to write this, and I don't benefit materially from you joining.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Choosing to take courses at &lt;a href="https://bradfieldcs.com/"&gt;Bradfield School of Computer Science&lt;/a&gt; is probably the best decision I've made for my career and my craft. If you're a software engineer, you should consider applying.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a loose collection of thoughts about my time in the &lt;a href="https://bradfieldcs.com/csi/"&gt;Computer Science Intensive (CSI)&lt;/a&gt; and at Bradfield generally. I wrote this to make a slightly more personal case for taking courses at Bradfield and to fill in some gaps in existing information. If you're totally unfamiliar with Bradfield, go read the &lt;a href="https://bradfieldcs.com/"&gt;official site&lt;/a&gt; first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Contents:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/bradfield-is-phenomenal/index.html#my-background-and-why-i-started-taking-bradfield-courses"&gt;My background and why I started taking Bradfield courses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/bradfield-is-phenomenal/index.html#who-takes-bradfield-courses"&gt;Who takes Bradfield courses?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/bradfield-is-phenomenal/index.html#quality-of-instruction"&gt;Quality of instruction&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/bradfield-is-phenomenal/index.html#workload"&gt;Workload&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/bradfield-is-phenomenal/index.html#value-in-interviews"&gt;Value in interviews&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/bradfield-is-phenomenal/index.html#value-on-the-job"&gt;Value on the job&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/bradfield-is-phenomenal/index.html#community"&gt;Community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/bradfield-is-phenomenal/index.html#money"&gt;Money&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/bradfield-is-phenomenal/index.html#accreditation"&gt;Accreditation&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/bradfield-is-phenomenal/index.html#other-students-reviews-of-bradfield"&gt;Other students' reviews of Bradfield&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/bradfield-is-phenomenal/index.html#closing-thoughts"&gt;Closing thoughts&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="my-background-and-why-i-started-taking-bradfield-courses"&gt;My background and why I started taking Bradfield courses&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I studied computer science and math at &lt;a href="https://www.wm.edu/"&gt;William &amp;amp; Mary&lt;/a&gt;, a public university in Virginia. I did well in school – I graduated &lt;em&gt;summa cum laude&lt;/em&gt;, was inducted into Phi Beta Kappa, and got a computer science department award.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I graduated with a lot of gaps in my computer science knowledge. I couldn't tell you how a computer physically operated, or how a database worked, or what an operating system's responsibilities were, or anything at all about computer networks. Some of this was because I was unlucky with course selection. The bigger reason is that I didn't absorb as much because I was learning to program at the same time I was learning computer science. These are different skills. Fighting to get a grip on language syntax and conventions occupied most of my attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After a few years of work, I was a much better programmer, but I started feeling the gaps in my computer science knowledge more acutely. I wondered why my code was slow and didn't have a good answer. I found out about Bradfield, and I signed up for a standalone course. It was more than I hoped it would be. I’ve now taken three standalone courses, and as of writing, I'm three modules into the CSI (about 1/3 of the way through). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="who-takes-bradfield-courses"&gt;Who takes Bradfield courses?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Students at Bradfield come from a broad range of backgrounds. Most are people who did coding bootcamps and have been working for at least a few years. Others studied computer science at university – some of my classmates at Bradfield have undergraduate degrees from the best computer science departments in the world. All of my classmates have gotten enormous value from Bradfield, I think in approximately equal measure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="quality-of-instruction"&gt;Quality of instruction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oz and Elliott, the instructors at Bradfield, are phenomenal teachers. Their knowledge of the subject matter is encyclopedic, but they also take teaching seriously as its own skill. Oz seems to read a lot of pedagogical theory (though he says not &lt;em&gt;too much&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/bradfield-is-phenomenal/index.html#note"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;), and Elliott continuously hones his courses. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The most important thing that Oz and Elliott teach is a mindset: that everything on a computer is knowable with a bit of effort. Need to figure out what's going on with a network? Open &lt;a href="https://www.wireshark.org/"&gt;Wireshark&lt;/a&gt; and capture some packets. Not sure what a certain system call is doing? Check the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Man_page"&gt;man page&lt;/a&gt;. Don't know how to use a protocol? Read the &lt;a href="https://www.rfc-editor.org/"&gt;RFC&lt;/a&gt;. Want to figure out how this language feature works? Go to the source code. When a student asks something and the instructor says "huh, I don't know," they find out and in the process show the rest of us how to answer our own questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A small list of other things I like about instruction at Bradfield:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A strong emphasis on learning by doing. Most class pre-work involves a hands-on exercise.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Historical motivation as a teaching method. The instructors will take us back to a historical context and ask us how we'd solve a problem to help us understand how the world ended up as it is.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tangents/rants. Get ready to hear about how programmers ought to be more like woodworkers and make more of their own tools, why the space / time complexity tradeoff is kind of a lie, and why microservices are not a great fit for most organizations.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="workload"&gt;Workload&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The CSI workload is heavy, there's no getting around that. You have two to three hour classes twice a week plus optional hour-long check-ins. Every class has pre-work. Expect to spend ten hours a week on CSI at minimum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Should you join CSI, you should expect to fall behind at some point. Don't let it psych you out. Keep showing up to class. Oz and Elliott won't get mad at you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're thorough, you can easily spend as much time on Bradfield as you do at a full-time job. It's absolutely not necessary, though – I only say this because some people in my cohort did this for a few months.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="value-in-interviews"&gt;Value in interviews&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Taking Bradfield courses makes you a stronger candidate when interviewing for jobs. Some of my classmates have interviewed for jobs at level &lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt; and done so well that they received offers at level &lt;em&gt;X&lt;/em&gt; + 1. I got offers that previously would have been unattainable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An example: I interviewed at an autonomous vehicle company last year. One of my interviewers was clearly perplexed when our session started and said outright that someone must have made a mistake. I had professionally only worked with Python, and his interview was about high-performance systems. "What's a Python programmer doing here," he said.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I said that while my experience was only Python and that I liked Python, I did care about performance and I understood why Python was slow. He said, fine, explain. So I used what I learned in Bradfield: I talked about how cache utilization in Python is bad for a few reasons (pointer-heavy data structures, everything is an object so takes more space, etc.). I was able to rattle off latency numbers to argue why this was so harmful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My interviewer’s demeanor changed completely. “It’s unusual for a Python programmer to think about caches at all.” He tested my knowledge a bit more, but the rest of the interview felt more like a friendly conversation than an interrogation. I had a great time, and I ended up with a good offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don’t think I would have passed this interview if not for my time at Bradfield. I was able to speak comfortably and confidently because I put the work in at Bradfield. I did the reading, and more importantly, the exercises, and that gave me a strong intuition for this stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;None of this is to say that you can just sign up for Bradfield and never have to study Leetcode-style problems again, but it makes you a lot stronger for everything else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="value-on-the-job"&gt;Value on the job&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bradfield's biggest benefit for me on the job has been simply having confidence that everything on a computer is knowable with a bit of effort. I can't give a dramatic example like I can with interviewing because real work isn't like interviewing, but I can tell you I'm faster and more capable, and that I have stronger engineering instincts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are some benefits more immediately related to class material. Just last week, I debugged some microservices by reading network activity directly. One of my classmates sped up a critical process by at least a factor of 2 (maybe a lot more?) by applying knowledge straight from a course. Another upgraded his whole company from HTTP/1.1 to HTTP/2.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="community"&gt;Community&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bradfield is the community of programmers I've been searching for. Students at Bradfield are serious in a low-ego, genuinely-trying-to-help-each-other way. It's energizing to be around other people with so much enthusiasm for the subject matter. I like being around everyone in my cohort without exception.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've tried joining other programming communities in the past, but they weren't what I was looking for. I found an undercurrent of insecurity and sweat that ruined the vibes for me. There's none of that at Bradfield.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="money"&gt;Money&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The year-long CSI is $19,500. The shorter 9-week course, &lt;a href="https://bradfieldcs.com/courses/ssba/"&gt;Software Systems: Behind the Abstractions&lt;/a&gt;, is $3,600. Either is worth it, easily. Sure, that's nothing to sneeze at, but it's cheap for what you get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm confident that if the CSI's price tag feels like too much, the program can get you to a place career-wise where it doesn't. Many students in CSI cohorts switch jobs, and some make twice as much as they did before. Recently, one quadrupled his income. I paid for CSI with a fraction of the signing bonus I got when I joined my current employer – a job I got thanks in large part to Bradfield courses.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obligatory disclaimer: the labor market is unusually hot right now so maybe don't count on doubling your income next year, but maybe don't count it out either.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="accreditation"&gt;Accreditation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bradfield is not an accredited school. I think you can get a certificate of completion if you ask for one? I don't know, whatever. That's not why you do Bradfield. You do Bradfield to attain mastery, to actually get better in real life. You do Bradfield because &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/oznova_/status/1479254530470518786"&gt;this stuff works&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seriously, though, we're lucky to work in an industry that &lt;a href="https://ozwrites.com/masters/"&gt;cares less about credentials than most others&lt;/a&gt;. There's some advantage to having a formal degree in computer science, but that largely ends after you get your first job.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="other-students-reviews-of-bradfield"&gt;Other students' reviews of Bradfield&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You don't just take it from me that Bradfield is great – other students have written even more thorough accounts of their time at Bradfield:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rohan wrote &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/RP-3/67c77a81274ba6ad4db9e27af8d014cc"&gt;My experience of the Bradfield Computer Science Intensive&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Julius wrote &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/rouxcaesar/9eced2261681efc268789f3fb2c8f958"&gt;My Thoughts on Bradfield&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clifford wrote &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/cliffordfajardo/03e580083a3b497e48fa52bfe3d6c04b"&gt;My Experience at Bradfield CS&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="closing-thoughts"&gt;Closing thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you're a software engineer, you'll likely benefit tremendously from courses at Bradfield. This stuff works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you have questions about Bradfield, you should reach out to them via their contact information on the &lt;a href="https://bradfieldcs.com/"&gt;Bradfield website&lt;/a&gt;. If you're looking for a student perspective, I'm happy to answer any questions via email at &lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/mailto:ivan@echevarria.io"&gt;ivan@echevarria.io&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1]&lt;i id="note"&gt;
Oz disputes that he read a lot on pedagogy: "[F]or the record, I don’t read up a whole bunch on pedagogy (some people *really* go overboard) but I do read some and do try to get actively better at teaching so I guess it’s the same sentiment :)"
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2022 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/bradfield-is-phenomenal/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/bradfield-is-phenomenal/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>January 2022</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;January was fun. I published a &lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/the-matrix-looks-different-hulu-hbo-max/index.html"&gt;blog post about streaming versions of the Matrix&lt;/a&gt;, and it unexpectedly blew up. I got a ton of traffic from Google – I'm still not quite sure what people were searching for that brought them to my site. A Japanese website published &lt;a href="https://gigazine.net/news/20220108-matrix-hulu-hbo-max-color/"&gt;a translation&lt;/a&gt; and called me a computer scientist. Delightful.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also continued the &lt;a href="https://bradfieldcs.com/csi/"&gt;Bradfield CSI&lt;/a&gt;. January covered computer networking, and it was, as Bradfield always is, excellent. I'm very eagerly looking forward to February's module: data structures for storage and retrieval.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="reading"&gt;Reading&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://leadelimination.org/"&gt;Lead Exposure Elimination Project&lt;/a&gt; published &lt;a href="https://leadelimination.org/annual-review-2020-21/"&gt;a review of their first year&lt;/a&gt;. Such incredible progress! I encourage you to &lt;a href="https://leadelimination.org/donate/"&gt;donate&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.noemamag.com/chinas-inclusive-authoritarianism/"&gt;China's Inclusive Authoritarianism&lt;/a&gt; was a super interesting article about the way China's authoritarian surveillance state actually makes it more democratically responsive to its citizens. I think it's bad to be an authoritarian surveillance state (hot take, I know), but it's plausible citizens could become attached because of the real utility they get from it. In the past year, I've become interested in understanding how systems that harm people still have appeal and utility. I've mostly focused on neoliberal capitalism from the 1970s until COVID, but this lens is fruitful when looking at present-day China too.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://moxie.org/stories/money-machine/"&gt;The Money Machine&lt;/a&gt; is a short anecdote about when the winning move is not to play. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://palladiummag.com/2022/01/06/quit-your-job/"&gt;Quit Your Job&lt;/a&gt; makes me want to quit my job. Not soon, but someday.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="watching"&gt;Watching&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did my annual get-HBO-for-a-month-and-then-cancel in mid-December, so I watched some HBO shows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;How To with John Wilson&lt;/em&gt; season 2 was more &lt;em&gt;How To with John Wilson&lt;/em&gt;, so it was great. The episode about Bang Energy drink was the highlight of the season for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Succession&lt;/em&gt; was okay. Maybe just stick to season 1? After finishing season 3, I was hit with an inescapable feeling that I had wasted a lot of time. The &lt;a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2021/12/13/on-succession-jeremy-strong-doesnt-get-the-joke"&gt;New Yorker article about how weird actor Jeremy Strong is&lt;/a&gt; is a lot more compelling than the show itself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="listening"&gt;Listening&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vegyn released  &lt;a href="https://vegyn.bandcamp.com/album/dont-follow-me-because-im-lost-too"&gt;Don't Follow Me Because I'm Lost Too!!&lt;/a&gt;, and I listened to it all the way through as soon as it came out. It made my day. Here's one of the many tracks I liked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe class="bandcamp-player" style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=3767420141/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/track=3027248650/transparent=true/" seamless&gt;&lt;a href="https://vegyn.bandcamp.com/album/dont-follow-me-because-im-lost-too"&gt;Don&amp;#39;t Follow Me Because I&amp;#39;m Lost Too!! by Vegyn&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 05 Feb 2022 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/january-2022/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/january-2022/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>The Matrix looks dramatically different on Hulu versus on HBO Max</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Comparison of HBO Max and Hulu " src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/the-matrix-looks-different-hulu-hbo-max/split.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="img-note"&gt;Hulu on the left, HBO Max on the right&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p class="note"&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Hulu stopped streaming &lt;i&gt;The Matrix&lt;/i&gt; on January 1, 2022.&lt;/b&gt; You can stream &lt;i&gt;The Matrix&lt;/i&gt; with an HBO Max subscription, or you can pay to rent it from your service of choice.
&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;
It seems like a lot of you are searching "the matrix hulu" and ending up on this page. This was not my goal. But this is what happened, so I figured I'd give you the information you're actually looking for.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;HBO Max has &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt; (1999) available for streaming, and Hulu did until a day or two ago, but their respective versions look very different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt; already has a history of extreme variation across versions. The initial DVD release had a neutral-warm color palette while the 2008 Blu-ray added a heavy green cast to match the sequels. &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt;'s 2018 UHD Blu-ray release apparently hews closer to how the film looked in theaters with a more purple-blue tint &lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/the-matrix-looks-different-hulu-hbo-max/index.html#note"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now it seems that this version fragmentation extends to streaming releases. The Hulu version had a strong green cast, and I suspect it used the 2008 Blu-ray version at its source. Meanwhile, the HBO Max version is more purple and blue, so it seems likely that it came from the 2018 UHD Blu-ray.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here are some comparisons with the HBO Max version on top and the Hulu version on the bottom:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="img-really-no-pad" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/the-matrix-looks-different-hulu-hbo-max/hbo6.jpg" alt="Screenshot of The Matrix from HBO Max"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Screenshot of The Matrix from Hulu" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/the-matrix-looks-different-hulu-hbo-max/hulu6.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hulu version's heavy green tint is apparent in this comparison. This is fairly representative of the versions' differences across the entire film.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="img-really-no-pad" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/the-matrix-looks-different-hulu-hbo-max/hbo7.jpg" alt="Screenshot of The Matrix from HBO Max"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Screenshot of The Matrix from Hulu" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/the-matrix-looks-different-hulu-hbo-max/hulu7.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Outdoor scenes in daylight get a little weird.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the shot above, you can see the green tint in Hulu's version, but you can also see that highlights roll off more gracefully. On the HBO Max version, Smith's forehead and the woman's blouse in the background are so bright that they lose definition.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="img-really-no-pad" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/the-matrix-looks-different-hulu-hbo-max/hbo2.jpg" alt="Screenshot of The Matrix from HBO Max"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Screenshot of The Matrix from Hulu" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/the-matrix-looks-different-hulu-hbo-max/hulu2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, the HBO Max version's highlights are way too bright, and the shadows on the building building's roof take on a too-bright cyan color. Hulu's version again has a green cast and controls its highlights better.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="img-really-no-pad" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/the-matrix-looks-different-hulu-hbo-max/hbo3.jpg" alt="Screenshot of The Matrix from HBO Max"/&gt;
&lt;img alt="Screenshot of The Matrix from Hulu" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/the-matrix-looks-different-hulu-hbo-max/hulu3.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another outdoor shot shows overcooked highlights on Neo's forehead in HBO Max's version while Hulu's handles them fine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The over-bright highlights on the HBO Max version makes me think there may have been an error in how the file was created for streaming. It looks like someone took an HDR image and did a bad conversion. Or maybe the HBO Max's version of &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt; looks great on a super high-end HDR display, and nobody tested it on more typical consumer devices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even if you ignore the highlights conundrum, you're still left with the problem that &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt; varies by streaming service. Some people genuinely like the green cast of the 2008 Blu-ray. Others want something closer to how it looked in theaters. When you steam &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt;, you don't know which version you're going to get, and that stinks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1]&lt;i id="note"&gt;
&lt;a href="https://youtu.be/KEdgmNZnLs4"&gt;This video&lt;/a&gt; goes into more detail about the history of Matrix remasters.
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2022 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/the-matrix-looks-different-hulu-hbo-max/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/the-matrix-looks-different-hulu-hbo-max/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>November / December 2021</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Happy belated New Year! I skipped November's update because I added a bunch of &lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/reading/https://www.echevarria.io/index.html"&gt;book reviews&lt;/a&gt; to this site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2021 was great. I gave a killer speech as best man at a wedding, I worked at three different companies (&lt;a href="https://www.setsail.co/"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://www.ladderlife.com/"&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://robinhood.com/"&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;), I did &lt;a href="https://www.recurse.com/"&gt;Recurse Center&lt;/a&gt;, I took three courses at &lt;a href="https://bradfieldcs.com/"&gt;Bradfield&lt;/a&gt;, I was admitted to and started the &lt;a href="https://bradfieldcs.com/csi/"&gt;Bradfield CSI&lt;/a&gt;, I &lt;a href="https://github.com/iechevarria/reading-notes/tree/master/2021"&gt;read more&lt;/a&gt; than I have since I was a child, and I &lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/https://www.echevarria.io/index.html"&gt;wrote more&lt;/a&gt; in public than I ever have.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="site-updates"&gt;Site updates&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I made a few updates to this site in the past two months. First, like I mentioned above, I added more than a dozen &lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/reading/https://www.echevarria.io/index.html"&gt;book reviews&lt;/a&gt;. I'm still working through my backlog. I also updated this site's &lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/index.html"&gt;home page&lt;/a&gt;, and there's now a section for popular posts. Finally, after a reader request, I added &lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/rss.xml"&gt;RSS&lt;/a&gt; support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="reading"&gt;Reading&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read &lt;em&gt;The Poverty of Historicism&lt;/em&gt; by Karl Popper in November. It was an odd book because it's so clearly of its time, making an impassioned argument in a dead debate I never knew existed. But there are gems in it, little pieces of common sense wisdom. I'll write about it more in the future, but for now you can read my &lt;a href="https://github.com/iechevarria/reading-notes/blob/master/2021/the-poverty-of-historicism-popper-1957.md"&gt;personal notes&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Slaughterhouse-Five&lt;/em&gt; lived up to its reputation. It was very good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read a New Yorker article, &lt;a href="https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2015/08/10/a-ghost-in-the-family"&gt;A Ghost in the Family&lt;/a&gt;, about artists Clare Rojas, Margaret Kilgallen, and Barry McGee after seeing a piece by Rojas in SFO. What a strange story.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jeff Vogel of &lt;a href="https://www.spiderwebsoftware.com/"&gt;Spiderweb Software&lt;/a&gt; wrote &lt;a href="https://bottomfeeder.substack.com/p/six-truths-about-video-game-stories"&gt;a piece about video game stories&lt;/a&gt;. Basically, narratives in games are typically terrible, and it doesn't take much to stand out. If you like this post, you might also enjoy his memorable GDC talk, &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=stxVBJem3Rs"&gt;Failing to Fail&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="watching"&gt;Watching&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I got an HBO Max subscription for just this month to watch &lt;em&gt;The Matrix Resurrections&lt;/em&gt;. It's a big mess that mostly makes fun of itself and Warner Brothers (by name) for existing. What a novelty it is to see so much money get lit on fire. I ended up watching &lt;em&gt;The Matrix&lt;/em&gt; (1999) again, and I like it more every time I see it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id="playing"&gt;Playing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I played the &lt;em&gt;Halo Infinite&lt;/em&gt; campaign the day it came out. &lt;a href="blog/october-2020/https://www.echevarria.io/index.html"&gt;I'm a big Halo fan&lt;/a&gt;. This one was ... pretty alright! It still has some of the problems that &lt;em&gt;Halo 4&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Halo 5&lt;/em&gt; did: tedious indoor combat and way too many buttons that need to be pressed. I'm thinking about doing a supercut of all the stupid buttons &lt;em&gt;Halo Infinite&lt;/em&gt;. But the open world is great, and the sandbox is super fun. I hope we'll see some updates to the single player that extend the open world and add new biomes like desert and jungle.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jan 2022 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/december-2021/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/december-2021/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Consistent daily price oscillations on the Steam Community Market</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/cs-go-price-oscillation/steam.png"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-really-no-pad" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/cs-go-price-oscillation/steam.png" alt="chart of CS:GO Operation Riptide Case median sales prices on Steam Community Market"/&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="img-note"&gt;click the image above to see a full-size version&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a chart of median sale prices of the most-sold item on the &lt;a href="https://steamcommunity.com/market/"&gt;Steam Community Market&lt;/a&gt;, an &lt;a href="https://steamcommunity.com/market/listings/730/Operation%20Riptide%20Case"&gt;Operation Riptide Case&lt;/a&gt; for Counter-Strike: Global Offensive (CS:GO).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The extremely regular oscillations in price jumped out to me immediately. You don't typically see this in other markets because it's a sign that money is being left on the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first instinct was that this pattern was somehow related to CS:GO player count, so I pulled historical price and volume data from Steam and historical player counts from &lt;a href="https://steamcharts.com/"&gt;steamcharts.com&lt;/a&gt; to made this chart:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/cs-go-price-oscillation/chart.svg"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-really-no-pad" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/cs-go-price-oscillation/chart.svg" alt="chart of CS:GO Operation Riptide Case median sales prices on Steam Community Market, player count, and transaction count"/&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="img-note"&gt;click the image above to see a full-size version&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="img-caption"&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Top&lt;/b&gt;: median sale price in dollars
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Middle&lt;/b&gt;: CS:GO player count
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Bottom&lt;/b&gt;: count of Operation Riptide Cases sold
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does look like it has something to do with player count. So what's happening? These cases are randomly given to players when they play the game, and some players immediately sell their cases for cash at market price. (If sellers cared about making a few extra cents, they could submit offers to sell above the current market price instead of selling at market price when prices are low.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect the oscillations are caused by different regions buying/selling/keeping cases at different rates. To illustrate, it might be the case that players in Europe sell more cases and buy fewer cases than players in the Americas, so the market price for cases is lower during European hours than American hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't see the same pattern in other CS:GO items. Only the Operation Riptide Case exhibits it, and that makes sense because it's the only item that is currently being distributed to players for simply playing the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why aren't there other market participants who flatten these oscillations out? Someone could buy cases cheap during European hours and sell for a profit during American hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The culprit here is fees on Steam Community Market transactions. CS:GO items on the Community Market are subject to a 15% fee on every transaction: 5% for Steam plus 10% for CS:GO specifically. This means that you can only make money on price swings greater than 15%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at the actual price daily swings, they're typically smaller than 15%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="img-really-no-pad" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/cs-go-price-oscillation/percents.svg" alt="Percentage difference between minimum hourly median and maximum hourly median sale price by day"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="img-note"&gt;
    Percentage difference between minimum hourly median and maximum hourly median sale price by day
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On some days, the percentage approaches 15%. I suspect that on these days, there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; some market participants buying cheap, holding for a few hours, selling high, and making a cent or two per case after fees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the min and max values used in the chart are median hourly sale price, so some transactions happened at higher/lower values. Therefore individual cases may have been bought and then sold profitably after fees.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/cs-go-price-oscillation/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/cs-go-price-oscillation/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>An interesting way to pack bytes into a MIDI SysEx message</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Here’s a little thought experiment: how would you transmit 8-bit bytes via messages that let you encode only 7 bits at a time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The engineers at &lt;a href="https://www.digitech.com/"&gt;DigiTech&lt;/a&gt; handled this exact problem on their DHP-55 effects unit in the 1990s. They needed to transmit 8-bit bytes to the unit via a MIDI SysEx message. Every byte in a SysEx message must have its most significant bit set to 0, so there are only 7 bits available per byte for sending data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how they describe their approach in the DHP-55 manual:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="todo2" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/midi-sysex/scan1.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For clarity, I'm going to call the 8-bit bytes we want to transmit the "real" bytes and the bytes with 7 bits available that we have to use the "send" bytes.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The engineers chose to do the following: pack 7 "real" bytes into 8 "send" bytes at a time. Take the most significant bit of each of the "real" bytes and put them into the first "send" byte. Then take the remaining 7 bits of each of the "real" bytes and put them in each of the remaining "send" bytes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've illustrated an example of this packing below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="todo" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/midi-sysex/midi-bits.svg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="img-caption"&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Left&lt;/b&gt;: The 7 (8-bit) "real" bytes we want to transmit
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Right&lt;/b&gt;: The 8 "send" bytes. The first byte contains 0 and the most significant bit of each of the 7 "real" bytes. The following 7 "send" bytes contain 0 and the 7 remaining bits of each of the 7 "real" bytes.
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find this a pretty interesting solution to the problem. It's not my first instinct – I would have just mashed the bytes together instead of sending the most significant bits separately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why the engineers at DigiTech separate the most significant bits? One reason might be that it makes hex dumps a lot easier to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you take a look at the manual, you can see that much of the data that's being transmitted is small integers (less than 128) where the most significant bit is already 0. This means that many of the "send" bytes will have identical values to those in the "real" bytes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bank number, preset number, number of effects, effect number, number of parameters, effect version – all of these will likely be less than 128.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="todo3" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/midi-sysex/scan2.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the DigiTech engineers had gone with my approach, "send" bytes would not resemble "real" bytes, and they wouldn't be able to use hex dumps for spot checks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you know another reason, please reach out!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/midi-sysex/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/midi-sysex/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>