<rss version="2.0">
  <channel>
  <title>echevarria.io</title>
  <description>Ivan Echevarria's blog</description>
  <link>https://www.echevarria.io</link>
  <item>
    <title>Consistent daily price oscillations on the Steam Community Market</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/cs-go-price-oscillation/steam.png"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-really-no-pad" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/cs-go-price-oscillation/steam.png" alt="chart of CS:GO Operation Riptide Case median sales prices on Steam Community Market"/&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="img-note"&gt;click the image above to see a full-size version&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a chart of median sale prices of the most-sold item on the &lt;a href="https://steamcommunity.com/market/"&gt;Steam Community Market&lt;/a&gt;, an &lt;a href="https://steamcommunity.com/market/listings/730/Operation%20Riptide%20Case"&gt;Operation Riptide Case&lt;/a&gt; for Counter-Strike: Global Offensive (CS:GO).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The extremely regular oscillations in price jumped out to me immediately. You don't typically see this in other markets because it's a sign that money is being left on the table.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My first instinct was that this pattern was somehow related to CS:GO player count, so I pulled historical price and volume data from Steam and historical player counts from &lt;a href="https://steamcharts.com/"&gt;steamcharts.com&lt;/a&gt; to made this chart:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/cs-go-price-oscillation/chart.svg"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-really-no-pad" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/cs-go-price-oscillation/chart.svg" alt="chart of CS:GO Operation Riptide Case median sales prices on Steam Community Market, player count, and transaction count"/&gt;
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="img-note"&gt;click the image above to see a full-size version&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="img-caption"&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Top&lt;/b&gt;: median sale price in dollars
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Middle&lt;/b&gt;: CS:GO player count
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Bottom&lt;/b&gt;: count of Operation Riptide Cases sold
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does look like it has something to do with player count. So what's happening? These cases are randomly given to players when they play the game, and some players immediately sell their cases for cash at market price. (If sellers cared about making a few extra cents, they could submit offers to sell above the current market price instead of selling at market price when prices are low.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I suspect the oscillations are caused by different regions buying/selling/keeping cases at different rates. To illustrate, it might be the case that players in Europe sell more cases and buy fewer cases than players in the Americas, so the market price for cases is lower during European hours than American hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't see the same pattern in other CS:GO items. Only the Operation Riptide Case exhibits it, and that makes sense because it's the only item that is currently being distributed to players for simply playing the game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But why aren't there other market participants who flatten these oscillations out? Someone could buy cases cheap during European hours and sell for a profit during American hours.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The culprit here is fees on Steam Community Market transactions. CS:GO items on the Community Market are subject to a 15% fee on every transaction: 5% for Steam plus 10% for CS:GO specifically. This means that you can only make money on price swings greater than 15%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look at the actual price daily swings, they're typically smaller than 15%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img class="img-really-no-pad" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/cs-go-price-oscillation/percents.svg" alt="Percentage difference between minimum hourly median and maximum hourly median sale price by day"/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="img-note"&gt;
    Percentage difference between minimum hourly median and maximum hourly median sale price by day
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On some days, the percentage approaches 15%. I suspect that on these days, there &lt;em&gt;are&lt;/em&gt; some market participants buying cheap, holding for a few hours, selling high, and making a cent or two per case after fees.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Note that the min and max values used in the chart are median hourly sale price, so some transactions happened at higher/lower values. Therefore individual cases may have been bought and then sold profitably after fees.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/cs-go-price-oscillation/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/cs-go-price-oscillation/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>An interesting way to pack bytes into a MIDI SysEx message</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;Here’s a little thought experiment: how would you transmit 8-bit bytes via messages that let you encode only 7 bits at a time?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The engineers at &lt;a href="https://www.digitech.com/"&gt;DigiTech&lt;/a&gt; handled this exact problem on their DHP-55 effects unit in the 1990s. They needed to transmit 8-bit bytes to the unit via a MIDI SysEx message. Every byte in a SysEx message must have its most significant bit set to 0, so there are only 7 bits available per byte for sending data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is how they describe their approach in the DHP-55 manual:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="todo2" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/midi-sysex/scan1.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(For clarity, I'm going to call the 8-bit bytes we want to transmit the "real" bytes and the bytes with 7 bits available that we have to use the "send" bytes.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The engineers chose to do the following: pack 7 "real" bytes into 8 "send" bytes at a time. Take the most significant bit of each of the "real" bytes and put them into the first "send" byte. Then take the remaining 7 bits of each of the "real" bytes and put them in each of the remaining "send" bytes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've illustrated an example of this packing below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="todo" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/midi-sysex/midi-bits.svg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="img-caption"&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Left&lt;/b&gt;: The 7 (8-bit) "real" bytes we want to transmit
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;b&gt;Right&lt;/b&gt;: The 8 "send" bytes. The first byte contains 0 and the most significant bit of each of the 7 "real" bytes. The following 7 "send" bytes contain 0 and the 7 remaining bits of each of the 7 "real" bytes.
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I find this a pretty interesting solution to the problem. It's not my first instinct – I would have just mashed the bytes together instead of sending the most significant bits separately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So why the engineers at DigiTech separate the most significant bits? One reason might be that it makes hex dumps a lot easier to read.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you take a look at the manual, you can see that much of the data that's being transmitted is small integers (less than 128) where the most significant bit is already 0. This means that many of the "send" bytes will have identical values to those in the "real" bytes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bank number, preset number, number of effects, effect number, number of parameters, effect version – all of these will likely be less than 128.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="todo3" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/midi-sysex/scan2.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If the DigiTech engineers had gone with my approach, "send" bytes would not resemble "real" bytes, and they wouldn't be able to use hex dumps for spot checks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If you know another reason, please reach out!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2021 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/midi-sysex/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/midi-sysex/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Casting pig iron at the Iroquois smelter</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Pig iron smelter" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/casting-pig-iron-at-the-iroquois-smelter/pig-iron.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;High-resolution scans of this image are available at the &lt;a href="https://www.loc.gov/resource/det.4a08071/"&gt;Library of Congress website&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This photograph shows men making pig iron at a place called the Iroquois smelter in Chicago sometime between 1890 and 1901. Molten iron was poured via a central channel to fill the small, regular trenches on the ground to form ingots. Once cooled, the ingots were broken apart from one another and readied for transport or storage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The smelter's brick structure has church-like arches, and the beams of light flowing through smoke suggest burning incense. The beauty is undeniable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But this image also contains evil. The same smoke that gives form to light was undoubtedly life-shortening for workers at the smelter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’m reminded of this passage from Robert Adams’s essay &lt;em&gt;Photographing Evil&lt;/em&gt; from his book &lt;a href="https://aperture.org/books/beauty-in-photography/"&gt;Beauty in Photography&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="quote"&gt;
"When we are young, we want art that is filled with the bitter facts, because we believe that evil can be overcome if we face it; when we grow older and begin to doubt this optimistic belief, we want art that does not simply reinforce the pain of our disillusionment.”
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photographs like this one meet the requirements of young and old alike; "[they] urge reform, but seem to suggest that the need for it is not the most important thing to be said of life."&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 21 Nov 2021 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/casting-pig-iron-at-the-iroquois-smelter/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/casting-pig-iron-at-the-iroquois-smelter/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>October 2021</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;I spent most of October studying and working. I'm currently in the Advanced Programming module of the &lt;a href="https://bradfieldcs.com/csi/"&gt;Bradfield CSI&lt;/a&gt; which covers the Go programming language in depth. Learning the guts behind some of Go's core features – goroutines, channels, the scheduler – has been rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;October was my second month working at a large tech company, and it's still good. One of the best parts of working at a larger-but-not-quite-enormous tech company is that I'm finally working hands-on with technologies that I only knew by name before. I've been having a lot of moments where I go something like &lt;em&gt;"oh that's what Airflow is for."&lt;/em&gt; It's not just that I have more tools, it's that I've seen how other people use them effectively.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Reading&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p class="quote"&gt;
"There is always a subjective aspect in landscape art, something in the picture that tells us as much about who is behind the camera as about what is in front of it."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did my annual re-read of Robert Adams's &lt;a href="https://aperture.org/books/beauty-in-photography/"&gt;Beauty in Photography&lt;/a&gt; in October. It's short – just eight brief essays in fewer than 100 pages of text – but it is so full of insight. It's probably the book that means the most to me. I first read it at an important time, and it was enormously clarifying for my own work. In particular, Adams's insistence that great landscape photographs must have an autobiographical element led me to my best photographs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Watching&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;div class="youtube-embed-container"&gt;        
  &lt;iframe
    src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/qfyEstdwWIE"
    frameborder="0"
    allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
    allowfullscreen
  &gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This short film about an diver who maintains Mexico City's sewage system is excellent. I'm not sure how I ended up on it, but I'm glad I did!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I saw Dune and thought it was great. I like everything Denis Villeneuve does, so that's not much of surprise.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;James Bond: New Sequel was not great. The first half was good, but the second half was bloated with a videogame-like body count and cloying ending. Also the big maguffin was NANOMACHINES. Stupid! I yearn for the days when 007's big mission is getting ahold of a special typewriter like in &lt;em&gt;From Russia with Love&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Listening&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://grouper.bandcamp.com/"&gt;Grouper&lt;/a&gt; released an album, &lt;a href="https://grouper.bandcamp.com/album/shade"&gt;Shade&lt;/a&gt;, in October. I particularly like the song Unclean Mind:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" class="bandcamp-player" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=3927818988/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/track=2090522723/transparent=true/" seamless&gt;&lt;a href="https://grouper.bandcamp.com/album/shade"&gt;Shade by Grouper&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've also been listening to &lt;a href="https://djseinfeld.bandcamp.com/"&gt;DJ Seinfeld&lt;/a&gt;'s new album, &lt;a href="https://djseinfeld.bandcamp.com/album/mirrors"&gt;Mirrors&lt;/a&gt;. I listened to this track a lot:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" class="bandcamp-player" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=2742410761/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/track=2607348065/transparent=true/" seamless&gt;&lt;a href="https://djseinfeld.bandcamp.com/album/mirrors"&gt;Mirrors by DJ Seinfeld &amp;amp; Teira&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 12 Nov 2021 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/october-2021/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/october-2021/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Integrity makes an impression</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;A lifetime ago, I worked on products at an early stage startup. One of these was an offering for live chat agents, the people who you message in the chat bubbles that pop up on web pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My team was a few weeks from launching a prototype with our first customer, and we presented our progress at a company all-hands. During that meeting, a coworker suggested that we go to the customer’s website and send a message to one of the chat agents live to show everyone how such a system usually works.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the co-founders immediately shot the idea down. “How would you like it if someone showed up unannounced and interrupted your work?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What I like most about the co-founder’s response is that he went straight for the moral reason. He didn’t say it could be bad for the business (it probably wouldn’t have been). To him, the biggest issue is that it wasn’t considerate – we shouldn’t waste a chat agent’s time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I still think about this brief exchange. When I left that company, I had an exit interview with that co-founder where I mentioned how much of an impression his response made on me. He didn’t remember it at all, even after I recounted it in detail. I realized his response was just a reflex for him, and I think that’s more evidence of his integrity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is the kind of person I want to work for or with: ethical and conscientious without even having to try.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sun, 07 Nov 2021 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/integrity-makes-an-impression/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/integrity-makes-an-impression/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>The value of running your adversary's strategy in-house</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This is written with the assumption that you know what a market maker is and what an order book is. For a solid primer, check out the &lt;a href="https://a16z.com/2021/02/17/payment-for-order-flow/"&gt;first three sections of this opinion piece&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If I should make any corrections to this post, please reach out.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Market making versus liquidity taking&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;High frequency trading (HFT) firms run strategies that broadly fall into two categories: making and taking. Market making strategies add bids and asks to trading venues’ order books, making it possible for other market participants to quickly convert a security into cash and vice-versa. Conversely, liquidity-taking strategies execute on existing bids or asks, removing them from order books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you make markets, one of your biggest risks is failing to cancel stale quotes. If the price of the security moves, your offers to sell could now be too low, or your quotes to buy could now be too high. Then when someone executes against those stale quotes, you lose money, and they make some. This is called being “picked off.” When you’re running a taking strategy, you’re actively looking for quotes that you can pick off: too-high bids and too-low asks are what you want to execute against.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is why speed matters so much in HFT: if you’re a market maker and you don’t cancel your stale quotes fast enough, a liquidity taker will execute on them and eat your lunch.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Building the adversary in-house&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Other than raw speed, how else can makers avoid getting picked off by takers? One interesting answer is that HFT firms doing market making should also have an in-house team running a taking strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The taking team hunts for stale quotes from any market participant. When they find a quote they can pick off for a profit, and it comes from outside the firm, they execute against the order and make some money. If the quote comes from inside the firm, they tell the market making team to cancel it so it won’t be picked off by a competitor &lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/value-of-in-house-adversary/index.html#note"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.sps.ed.ac.uk/staff/donald-mackenzie"&gt;Donald MacKenzie&lt;/a&gt; describes the (unintended) results of such an approach in his book &lt;a href="https://press.princeton.edu/books/hardcover/9780691211381/trading-at-the-speed-of-light"&gt;Trading at the Speed of Light&lt;/a&gt; (p 195):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="quote"&gt;
“Attempts to take ... had the unintended, emergent consequence of increasing the profitability of the firm's market making algorithms. The latter would be to a degree protected from taking algorithms in the wider market by the fact that one of the firm's own taking algorithms might well cause the cancellation of a making order before it could be picked off"
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The taking team protected the whole firm’s profitability not by directly looking for flaws in the making team’s strategy – it was a black box to them – but simply by trying to pick off any market participant. Having a taking mindset and taking incentives helped the team find and plug holes in the firm’s making strategy that the making team didn’t know about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The HFT maker/taker relationship is inherently adversarial, and having both sides within the same firm partially insulates it from outside competitors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br&gt;
&lt;br&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1]&lt;i id="note"&gt;
This is a slightly inaccurate simplification – I didn’t want to muddy the explanation. The taking team doesn’t directly tell the making team to cancel their order because the taking team doesn't actually know which orders belong to them. The taking team just sees an order they want to execute against and a separate system within the firm decides whether to execute against it (another firm’s order) or cancel it (the firm's order).
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 06 Nov 2021 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/value-of-in-house-adversary/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/value-of-in-house-adversary/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>September 2021</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;My cohort of the &lt;a href="https://bradfieldcs.com/csi/"&gt;Bradfield CSI&lt;/a&gt; started in earnest last month, and it has been exceptional as Bradfield always is. So far the most mind-blowing part has been learning about and doing low-level optimization – doing loop unrolling, inlining functions, exploiting microarchitecture. It feels like black magic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I also joined a &lt;a href="https://robinhood.com/"&gt;larger tech company&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;a href="https://careers.robinhood.com/"&gt;hiring&lt;/a&gt;) in September, and so far my experience has been good. Coming from startups, there’s a lot to like – mature engineering practices, formalized onboarding, incredible scale, and, let’s face it, better pay. In hindsight, I shouldn’t have been as apprehensive as I was to join a bigger company.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Watching&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chris at Clickspring is back with more videos about the Antikythera mechanism. In this one, he speculates about what the workshop where the mechanism was built was like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="youtube-embed-container"&gt;        
  &lt;iframe
    src="https://www.youtube-nocookie.com/embed/BLBDKmFG90U"
    frameborder="0"
    allow="accelerometer; autoplay; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture"
    allowfullscreen
  &gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Reading&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Matthew C. Klein wrote two solid free posts this month in &lt;a href="https://theovershoot.co/"&gt;The Overshoot&lt;/a&gt;, his newsletter about macroeconomics. In &lt;a href="https://theovershoot.co/p/the-federal-reserve-wonders-what"&gt;The Federal Reserve Wonders What "Maximum Employment" Means&lt;/a&gt;, he examines the Fed consistently underestimated maximum employment in the wake of the Great Recession and how that’s interacting with Fed policy today. In &lt;a href="https://theovershoot.co/p/americas-inflation-story-is-entering"&gt;America's Inflation Story Is Entering a New Phase&lt;/a&gt;, Klein looks at where and why inflation is showing up. For example:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="quote"&gt;
“The possibility that some hotels, airlines, and car rental agencies increased prices too much over the summer in the expectation of a snapback of price-insensitive business travel, and are now reversing course”
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love this kind of thinking about inflation – the focus on very specific mechanisms instead of “quantity of money go up, inflation do up.” That’s not to say that the quantity of money doesn’t affect inflation. But it’s important to lay out channels and mechanisms to make plausible hypotheses about when and where it will appear.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dan Luu wrote &lt;a href="https://danluu.com/in-house/"&gt;another winner&lt;/a&gt; this month, this time on the value of in-house expertise. Why does Twitter have a kernel team? Because at a certain scale, you run into kernel problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/234730/zero-to-one-by-peter-thiel-with-blake-masters/"&gt;Zero to One&lt;/a&gt; by Peter Thiel was excellent. What I like most is his disdain for competition (informed by philospher René Girard).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="quote"&gt;
"More than anything else, competition is an ideology––the ideology––that pervades our society and distorts our thinking. We preach competition, internalize its necessity, and enact its commandments; and as a result, we trap ourselves within it––even though the more we compete, the less we gain."
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do you avoid competition? You differentiate yourself by choosing a path, making a plan, and committing to it. Optimizing for optionality is a great way to get stuck in a highly competitive profession that makes you miserable and dulls your achievement.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(On a similar note, I re-read Byrne Hobart’s piece &lt;a href="https://byrnehobart.medium.com/reasoning-from-first-principles-the-dumbest-thing-smart-people-do-46ff1cbba867"&gt;Reasoning From First Principles: The Dumbest Thing Smart People Do&lt;/a&gt;. You can see a lot of Thiel’s influence there.)&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Fri, 08 Oct 2021 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/september-2021/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/september-2021/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Give now, not later</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in giving to charity, you should give now instead of later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I give at least 10% of my income to charity each month. When a friend found out that I do this, he said that a better approach would be to save and invest that money, and then bequeath the compounded sum to charity after death. I disagree – giving now instead of giving later is better for a few reasons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Prevention instead of mitigation&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, many charitable organizations focus on preventing harm instead of mitigating it. This matters because many harms compound faster than money does in an investment account. For example, the &lt;a href="https://leadelimination.org/"&gt;Lead Exposure Elimination Project&lt;/a&gt; (LEEP) works to prevent lead exposure, which is known to cause an array of harms. Because LEEP focuses on prevention instead of mitigation, they’re able to be orders of magnitude more cost-effective than the alternative. You’re a lot better off just keeping lead out of kids’ blood than you are trying to fix the problems some decades down the line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I think about giving, I think about giant sequoia stumps. In the 1800s, people cut down giant sequoias that had grown for thousands of years. Once they were cut, there was no going back – no amount of prioritization or mitigation brings those ancient trees back to life. Many things work the same way, where harm is easy to cause (and prevent) but difficult or impossible to reverse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Are you sure you’ll give in the future?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another reason to give now is just to have certainty that you actually will give. Are you &lt;em&gt;sure&lt;/em&gt; you’ll give in the future? You don’t know how you’ll change. If you care about giving now, it’s smart to hedge against the possibility of a less enthusiastic future self, or worse, the possibility that you’ll turn into a bona fide asshole. It happens to a lot of people!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Building a habit of giving&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Giving regularly now also helps build a habit of giving.  When you make giving a habit, you’re not just hedging against some future self that won’t give, you’re actively changing yourself into a person who does give in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are secondary benefits to having a habit of giving. I personally have gotten better at finding promising organizations (like LEEP). I’m also more thoughtful about the way I spend money, and I find that I’m now on average happier with the things I do buy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’re interested in giving now and building a habit of giving, you can join &lt;a href="https://www.givingwhatwecan.org/"&gt;Giving What We Can&lt;/a&gt;. I joined in 2019, and I’ve been very happy with the decision.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 18 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/give-now-not-later/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/give-now-not-later/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>July / August 2021</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;The last two months were a bit of a whirlwind. First, I left my job, the one I joined only a few months earlier. Not a good look for me! But I’m confident it was the right decision. My long-term goals changed recently, and my work didn’t align with them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from off-boarding and trying to figure out what I want to do with myself, I spent a solid portion of July and August in &lt;a href="https://bradfieldcs.com/"&gt;Bradfield&lt;/a&gt;’s computer networking course. It was – as all Bradfield classes are – great!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In August, I started the Bradfield &lt;a href="https://bradfieldcs.com/csi/"&gt;Computer Science Intensive&lt;/a&gt;, a year-long program. So far, I’ve been brushing up on C, learning Go, and getting better at using the Unix shell.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Listening&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This episode of &lt;a href="https://oxide.computer/podcasts/kenneth-finnegan"&gt;On the Metal&lt;/a&gt; with Kenneth Finnegan was just fantastic. This story of a one-man &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Autonomous_system_(Internet)"&gt;autonomous system&lt;/a&gt; helped me understand so much of the material and political realities of the internet. And it was so much fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe class="bandcamp-player" src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/episode/7M0OeRSO5AFyLlr2wrQW5Q" width="100%" height="152" frameBorder="0" allowtransparency="true" allow="encrypted-media"&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also listened to a lot of &lt;a href="https://mansurbrown.bandcamp.com/"&gt;Mansur Brown&lt;/a&gt;’s music this month.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe class="bandcamp-player" style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;" src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=3539685109/size=small/bgcol=ffffff/linkcol=0687f5/track=2136873654/transparent=true/" seamless&gt;&lt;a href="https://mansurbrown.bandcamp.com/album/shiroi-2"&gt;Shiroi by Mansur Brown&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;Reading&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I finally finished &lt;a href="https://press.princeton.edu/books/hardcover/9780691211381/trading-at-the-speed-of-light"&gt;Trading at the Speed of Light&lt;/a&gt; in August, and I’d definitely recommend it to anyone who’s interested in how and why financial markets function as they do. In the next month or two, I think I’ll likely read &lt;a href="https://mitpress.mit.edu/books/engine-not-camera"&gt;An Engine, Not a Camera&lt;/a&gt;, another book by the same author.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nadiaeghbal.com/"&gt;Nadia Eghbal&lt;/a&gt; wrote &lt;a href="https://nadiaeghbal.com/asu"&gt;an article about Arizona State University&lt;/a&gt;, which prioritized access (de-emphasized selectiveness) while also improving its reputation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dan Luu’s &lt;a href="https://danluu.com/why-benchmark/"&gt;post about the importance of measurement&lt;/a&gt; was great. Some previous work with metrics (total epistemological nightmare) turned me into an enormous data skeptic, which I think was an overcorrection. This article helped me remember that yes, metrics &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; be meaningful and useful as long as you choose the right ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This &lt;a href="https://adamtooze.substack.com/p/chartbook-34-how-we-paid-for-the"&gt;post by Adam Tooze&lt;/a&gt; makes the point that the money spent on the War on Terror didn’t actually crowd out or prevent social spending – it’s just that social spending wasn’t a priority. I will never give up a chance to bang on this drum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Writing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hit the front page of Hacker News for the first time (&lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28418105"&gt;thread link&lt;/a&gt;)! It’s funny because the post, &lt;a href="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/flowers-make-a-nice-gift/index.html"&gt;Flowers make a nice gift&lt;/a&gt;, is easily the least time-intensive one on this site. I’m glad it resonated with people, though! I had a genuinely great time reading all the comments in the thread.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My favorite is &lt;a href="https://news.ycombinator.com/item?id=28418999"&gt;this one&lt;/a&gt;: “Was this some kind of HN ranking hack or are we really this lacking in news today? Or perhaps so socially stunted as a group that we need this sort of thing pointed out? Wait, maybe don’t answer that.”&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/august-2021/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/august-2021/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  <item>
    <title>Flowers make a nice gift</title>
    <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="photograph of sunflowers" src="https://www.echevarria.io/blog/flowers-make-a-nice-gift/sunflowers.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I was younger, I didn’t understand giving flowers as a gift. Flowers don’t last very long – wouldn’t it be better to get a gift that lasts a lifetime? It seemed wasteful to me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But now I appreciate flowers. Flowers don’t take any effort on your part to be enjoyed. You don’t have to use them, or read them, or find a permanent place on a shelf or in a drawer for them. Flowers never sit unused in a cardboard box that you packed two moves ago. And when you open that box by chance, you don't need to make any fraught decisions about whether or not to keep them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Flowers come without any obligations. They come into your home, and they bring beauty for a time, and then they’re gone. And that’s nice.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    <pubDate>Sat, 04 Sep 2021 00:00:00 -0000</pubDate>
    <link>blog/flowers-make-a-nice-gift/index.html</link>
  <guid isPermaLink="true">blog/flowers-make-a-nice-gift/index.html</guid>
  </item>
  </channel>
</rss>